Welles Family Correspondence, 1825-1929
Connecticut Historical Society
Welles Family Correspondence
1825-1929
Connecticut Historical Society, Hartford, Connecticut
Welles Family
1 linear foot (2 boxes)
Biographical Sketch
J. Leslie Welles (d. 1909) married Helena Griswold. Their children included Ruth Morris, Eleanor Margaret (1887-1968), Emily Adams, Clifford Yale (ca. 1881-), and Clayton Wolcott (b. 1883).
Scope and Content
The dealer who had this collection organized the letters according to the name of the recipient. They have since been reorganized by author, where possible, and arranged alphabetically by first name.
The collection consists of chatty family correspondence among members of the Welles family of Wethersfield. Son Clifford wrote from Pennsylvania about his surveys for an oil pipeline. He also advised Ruth about college and exercise before she left for Mount Holyoke. Based on his own letters while he was at Yale, Clifford knew money was tight, as he needed to conserve paper and reported that his socks had holes and his trousers had sprung a leak. He also pondered what to do as a career and attended Progressive Club meetings.
Emily, Eleanor and Ruth all attended Mount Holyoke College. The girls generally wrote about classes, needing money, playing sports (particularly basketball), gym class, visiting museums, etc. Most of Eleanor’s incoming correspondence was sympathy letters sent upon her father’s death in 1909. In her own letters, Eleanor mentioned how important it was to have a male companion at a gathering, but then found a sermon on the “inspiration of wifehood” highly amusing. She proudly boasted about being elected president of the debating club, and then debated the topic, “farming 50 years ago was more profitable than today.” Her later letters indicate she worked for the Office of the Surgeon General in the War Department in 1920.
Emily seemed to court trouble. In 1903, she wrote to Ruth that she had to hide her letter from the teacher and she described her escapades stealing grapes and pears. On a more serious note, she attended meetings of the Ladies’ Aid Society. She also mentions a hurricane that struck in October 1907.
Helena kept her daughters up on the family news and the progress of the garden while they were at college. In addition, she mentioned her activities with the Ladies’ Aid Society and the Women’s Christian Temperance Union.
Ruth’s incoming correspondence primarily came from friends and cousins. Her letters to her sisters included such topics as Roosevelt’s visit to Mount Holyoke, Holyoke’s President Hyde’s speech about the ideal woman and how the strain of academic work can harm their health. He advocated no exams for women. Evidently neither the students nor the faculty were amused. In 1906 Ruth taught at the YMCA in Holyoke and in 1910 traveled to Tennessee to teach at Howard College.
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions on access to the collection.
Accruals
The collection is closed.
Subject Headings
Personal Names
Welles, Helena Griswold.; Welles, Clifford Yale, b. ca. 1881.; Welles, Eleanor Margaret, 1887-1968.; Welles, Emily Adams.; Welles, Ruth Morris.
Subjects
Welles family.
Contents:
- Papers
  - Clifford Welles to parents, 1898, 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clifford Welles to sister Ruth, 1902-1904 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Eleanor Welles incoming correspondence, 1906-1909 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
  - Eleanor Welles to sister Emily Welles, 1907-1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - Eleanor Welles to sister Ruth Welles, 1903-1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eleanor Welles to parents, 1906-1910, undated (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
  - Eleanor Welles outgoing correspondence, 1920, 1921, undated (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Eleanor Welles report cards, 1904-1906 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Emily Welles incoming letters, (some partial pages), 1904, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Emily Welles to sister Eleanor Welles, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Emily Welles to sister Ruth Welles, 1903-1907 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Emily Welles to mother, 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Emily Welles outgoing correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Helena G. Welles incoming letters from Sunday School students, 1873 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Helena G. Welles incoming correspondence from family, 1873-1909 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Helena G. Welles incoming letters from sister Emily, 1904-1909 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Helena G. Welles to daughter Eleanor Welles, 1906-1907 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Helena G. Welles to daughter Ruth Welles, 1903-1911, undated (Box 2, Folder 5-7)
  - Helena G. Welles outgoing correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - J. Leslie Welles incoming correspondence, 1871, 1877 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Ruth Welles incoming correspondence, 1903-1910, undated (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - Ruth Welles to sister Eleanor Welles, 1904, 1910-1911 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Ruth Welles to sister Emily Welles, 1904-1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Ruth Welles to parents, 1904-1911, 1904-1911, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-21)
  - Ruth outgoing correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - “Fourth Book of Chronicles”, pencil sketch of tree and building, daily schedule, dance card for event at Wethersfield Grange, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Assorted letters to Nellie Welles, to and from Elizabeth Willard, and others, 1825, 1923-1929 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)